Guide to the Charles F. Kindred and Sarah E. Kindred Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Charles F. Kindred and Sarah E. Kindred papers
1870-1918
WA MSS S-3270
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
7.67
(15 containers)
The Charles F. Kindred and Sarah E. Kindred Papers, which span from circa 1870-1918, contain correspondence, mortgages, land deeds, maps, tax bills, business ledgers, printed material, legal papers, and other personal papers relating to Charles F. Kindred, Sarah E. Kindred, and their real estate dealings in Minnesota and North Dakota.
Kindred, Charles F., 1847-
Kindred, Sarah E., 1849-1907
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased from Michael Vinson on the Frederick W. and Carrie S. Beinecke Fund for Western Americana Fund, 2017.
Arrangement
Material within this collection maintains the original organization found at time of acquisition and are predominantly grouped by geographic location.
Sarah E. Kindred
Sarah E. Kindred (nee Chase) was born in Kidderminster, England in 1849. She later moved to the United States with her family, living in Chicago and Philadelphia before marrying Charles F. Kindred in 1875. The Kindreds lived on a farm located near Valley City, North Dakota in the early 1880's. Kindred was well-known for her philanthropy, particularly in Philadelphia where the couple also maintained a residence. She died from typhoid fever in 1907.
Charles F. Kindred
Charles Firman Kindred was born in Clifton, New Jersey in 1846. Charles and Sarah married on June 15, 1875 in Chicago, Illinois.
As early as 1874, Charles F. Kindred was working for the land department of the Northern Pacific Railroad in Minnesota. Later he served as assistant agent for the Great Northern Railroad. Kindred and his wife purchased considerable real estate in Minnesota and North Dakota. Their model farm, located near Valley City, North Dakota, comprised some 6,600 acres. Kindred was President of the Dakota Land Company and invested in a variety of utilities, particularly in Brainerd, Minnesota, where he maintained a home.
In 1880, Kindred resigned as assistant land commissioner of the Northern Pacific Railroad. In 1881 he was appointed assistant land commissioner for the Canadian Pacific Railroad Company. He also served as an agent for the Great Northern Railroad. Kindred was active in Republican politics at the local, state, and national levels. He opened a residence in Philadelphia in 1880 and appears to have traveled between Minnesota, North Dakota, and Philadelphia for several years. In 1888, when he became General Agent of the Philadelphia and Reading Railroad, he and his wife moved permanently to Philadelphia, but maintained their investments in western real estate and utilities. In 1900 Kindred purchased the Philadelphia Times, serving as President of the newspaper until it merged with The Public Ledger in 1902.
Kindred died in 1918.
Scope and Contents
The Charles F Kindred and Sarah E Kindred Papers, which span from circa 1870 to 1918, document the couple's investments, individually and jointly, in Minnesota and North Dakota real estate as well as in a variety of utility companies in Brainerd, Minnesota. Although there are some documents from as early as 1874, the bulk of the collection documents business transactions from the 1880s. The collection includes correspondence, mortgages, land deeds, maps, tax bills, business ledgers, and miscellaneous papers documenting legal actions concerning the Kindred's real estate and utility investments. A portion of these papers document Sara Kindred's personal investments.
The utility companies documented in the papers include Brainerd Water Company; Brainerd Water and Power Company; Mississippi Water Power and Boom Company; Brainerd Dam; Brainerd Dam and Raceway; Brainerd Light and Power; Brainerd Street Railway; and Brainerd Gas Plant. A considerable portion of the papers concern the Kinderd's model farm located near Valley City, North Dakota. The records include examples of Red Lake and Pembina Band of Chippewa Land Script receipts as well as patents for Sioux and Red Lake/Pembina lands.
The papers include materials documenting Republican Party campaign efforts in Minnesota circa 1880.
Businessmen -- Dakota Territory; Real property -- Dakota Territory; Land settlement -- North Dakota; Indian land transfers -- Minnesota; Land settlement -- Minnesota; Public utilities -- Minnesota; Real property -- Minnesota; Philanthropists -- Pennsylvania -- Philadelphia; Women -- West (U.S.) -- History; Brainerd (Minn.); Dakota Territory; Dakota Territory -- Economic conditions -- 19th century; Dakota Territory -- Economic conditions -- 20th Century; Minnesota; Minnesota -- Economic conditions -- 19th century; Minnesota -- Economic conditions -- 20th Century; Minnesota -- Politics and government -- 19th century; Minnesota -- Politics and government -- 20th Century; Valley City (N.D.); Businessmen -- North Dakota -- 19th century; Philanthropists -- Pennsylvania -- Philadelphia; Indian Land Transfers—North Dakota; Red Lake Band of Chippewa Indians—Land tenure; Pembina Band of Chippewa Indians—Land tenure; Indians of North America -- Land tenure; Kindred, Charles F., 1847-; Kindred, Sarah E., 1849-1907; Republican Party (U.S.: 1854- )
- North Dakota, city of Valley City--William Craswell, auditor, 1894-1898; 2 folders (Box 1)
  Scope and Contents
  Correspondence to Sarah Kindred including some financial documents.
- North Dakota--letters from John O. Oie, Cooperstown, 1895-1901; 2 folders (Box 1)
  Correspondence to Sara Kindred including one letter from Charles C. Piatt and financial documents.
- North Dakota--letters from J. Rosholt, First National Bank, Mayville, circa 1891-1895 (Box 1)
  Correspondence to Sara Kindred including one land title document.
- North Dakota--correspondence with George Saunders, John Saunders, and Robert Saunders, Gallatin, circa 1895-1901 (Box 1)
  Correspondence with Sara Kindred.
- North Dakota--correspondence with G. A. White, Portland State Bank, Portland, circa 1896 (Box 1)
  Correspondence between Sara Kindred and W.A. White of Portland State Bank.
- Minnesota--letters from City Bank, Minneapolis, 1888- (Box 1)
  Letters from City Bank in Minneapolis, concerning Sara and Charles Kindred.
- North Dakota--correspondence with Bennet and Daley Restaurant, Valley City, circa 1896-1898 (Box 1)
  Correspondence between Sara Kindred and Bennet and Daley Restaurant.
- North Dakota--letters from Frank L. Kellogg, Windsor, 1900- (Box 1)
  Letters from Frank L. Kellogg, real estate dealer.
- North Dakota--correspondence with Charles C. Piatt, Cooperstown, 1896-1900 (Box 1)
  Correspondence between Sara Kindred and Charles C. Piatt, from Cooperstown and Griggs Co., ND.
- North Dakota--correspondence with J.E. Erickson, Steele Co., 1890- (Box 1)
  One letter from J.E. Erickson to Sarah Kindred, and one instance of correspondence between Charles Kindred and Erickson.
- Dakota Territory--letters from New England Investment Co., Grand Forks, 1890- (Box 1)
  Letters from New England Investment Co. to Sara Kindred.
- North Dakota--correspondence with First National Bank, Valley City, circa 1895-98 (Box 1)
  Correspondence between Sara Kindred and John Tracy of First National Bank, Valley City ND.
- North Dakota--business correspondence, circa 1890-1903 (Box 1)
  Correspondence between Sara Kindred and multiple businesses in North Dakota.
- Dakota Territory, North Dakota--deeds and mortgages, circa 1881-1889; 2 folders (Box 1)
  Deeds and mortgages from the Dakota Territory and North Dakota related to Sara Kindred's real estate holdings.
- Dakota Territory, North Dakota--tax receipts, circa 1880s-1890s; 2 folders (Box 1)
  Tax receipts from multiple Dakota counties.
- Newspaper clippings, circa 1880s-1907; 2 folders (Box 1)
  Envelope containing newspaper clippings from the 1880s and 1890s, including one clipping concerning the death and estate of Sara Kindred.
- Philadelphia--bond receipt, 1912- (Box 1)
  Bond receipt concerning Charles Kindred and the sale of Sara Kindred's estate.
- Minnesota--letters from Leon L. Lum, Duluth, Brainerd, 1893-1906 (Box 2)
  Letters from Leon L. Lum, attorney, on both his own letterhead and First National Bank, Brainerd, MN letterhead. Includes some financial documents.
- Minnesota--correspondence with Alderman & Mantor, and Lovie Smith, Brainerd, 1904-1905 (Box 2)
  Correspondence between Sara Kindred and Alterman and Mantor (attorneys), as well as letters from Lovie Smith.
- Minnesota--correspondence with Thomas S. Finney, Park Rapids, 1902- (Box 2)
  Correspondence between Sara Kindred and Thomas S. Finney, real estate dealer. Includes contracts for deed.
- Chicago--letters from J.G. Harlow & Co., 1898- (Box 2)
  Letters from J.G. Harlow and Co., real estate dealers and managers, concerning flats being managed.
- Minnesota--business correspondence, circa 1895-1918 (Box 2)
  Correspondence between Sara Kindred and multiple Minnesota businesses; includes a land map and financial documents.
- Minnesota--general land office certificates, 1888- (Box 2)
  General Land Office certificates granted under Public Lands Act of 1820, includes Grover Cleveland signatures.
- Minnesota--general land office certificates, 1889 (Box 2)
  General land office certificates granting land under Public Lands Act of 1820, includes Benjamin Harrison signatures.
- Minnesota--deeds, abstracts, mortgages, tax bills, circa 1885-1891 (Box 2)
- Minnesota--deeds, abstracts, mortgages, tax bills, circa 1894-1900 (Box 2)
- North Dakota--photograph of Kindred Farm, Valley City, undated (Box 2)
  Photograph of Kindred farm, Valley City, ND on Northern Pacific Railroad photographer stationary.
- Dakota Territory--valuation of Kindred Farm including statement of expenses and profits, 1883 (Box 2)
  Documentation of the scope, location, expenses and profits of the Kindred Farm in Valley City, Dakota Territory.
- Receipt and bill ledger, circa 1887-1896 (Box 3)
  Receipt and bill ledger belonging to Sara Kindred, containing miscellaneous rent receipts for her lands.
- North Dakota--letters from W.A. Kindred, circa 1889-1891 (Box 4)
  Letters from Charles Kindred's brother, William 'Alfred" Kindred.
- North Dakota--letters from F.E. Snow and R.E. Hunt, 1891- (Box 4)
  Letters from F.E. Snow concerning Alfred Kindred's estate after death. Also includes a letter from R.E. Hunt.
- North Dakota--letters from F.E. Kindred, circa 1890-1914 (Box 4)
  Letters from F.E. Kindred.
- North Dakota--letters from Sister Jane and Lillian Kindred, 1890-1903 (Box 4)
  Letters from Sister Jane, Lillian Kindred, includes note made by Sara Kindred.
- North Dakota--letters from law offices, 1890-1894 (Box 4)
  Letters from a variety of law offices in North Dakota.
- North Dakota--letters from Charles Joslin, 1891-1894 (Box 4)
  Letters from Charles Joslin, attorney, most from North Dakota though includes stationary from Minnesota.
- North Dakota--letters from John Oie and R. Lunde, Cooperstown, 1892-1903 (Box 4)
  Letters from John Oie, R. Lunde, real estate dealers, including financial documents.
- North Dakota--letters from City of Valley City, Valley City High School, 1890-1899 (Box 4)
  Letters from City of Valley City, and Valley City High School, North Dakota, signed by Auditor William Craswell.
- North Dakota--letters from County of Cass, 1889-1894 (Box 4)
  Letters from County of Cass, North Dakota.
- North Dakota--letters from J.B. Folsom, 1890-1891 (Box 4)
  Letters from J.B. Folsom, real estate dealer.
- North Dakota--letters from Winterer and Winterer law office, 1890-1902 (Box 4)
- North Dakota--letters from Steele county and Griggs county, 1889-1898 (Box 4)
  Letters from Steele County and Griggs County, North Dakota.
- North Dakota--letters from H.P. Smart, 1890-1891 (Box 4)
  Related Materials
  Letters from H.P Smart, Cooperstown North Dakota.
- Minnesota and North Dakota--letters from Davis, Kellogg and Severance, 1894-1896 (Box 4)
  Letters from Davis, Kellogg and Severance, attorneys in St. Paul Minnesota, including 1892 court summons from County of Cass, North Dakota.
- North Dakota--letters from J.K Flynn, Fargo, 1890- (Box 4)
  Letters from J.K Flynn, many on Fargo North Dakota Fire Department letterhead.
- North Dakota--letters from Third District court, 1890-1895 (Box 4)
  Letters from Third Judicial Disctrict, District Court, North Dakota.
- North Dakota--letters from J.P. Dosh, 1888-1890 (Box 4)
  Letters from J.P. Dosh, attorney in New York, concerning Trail County North Dakota and other matters.
- Dakota Territory and North Dakota--letters from John J. Skuse, Fargo, 1879-1890 (Box 4)
  Letters from John J. Skuse, attorney in Fargo North Dakota.
- North Dakota--First National Bank, Hillsboro, 1890- (Box 4)
  Letters from First National Bank, Hillsboro North Dakota, including telegrams.
- North Dakota--letters from Darling and Angell, Fargo, 1895-1896 (Box 4)
  Letters from Darling and Angell, real estate and loans dealers, Fargo North Dakota.
- North Dakota--letters from First National Bank, Mayville, 1890-1891 (Box 4)
  Letters from First National Bank, Mayville North Dakota.
- North Dakota--letters from M.B. Cassell, 1890-1896 (Box 4)
  Letters from M.B. Cassell, register of deeds, Steele County North Dakota.
- North Dakota--letters from William Glass, Cooperstown, 1896-1897 (Box 4)
  Letters from William Glass, real estate and loans, Cooperstown North Dakota.
- North Dakota--letters from Ole Hertsgaard, 1890- (Box 4)
  Letters from Ole Hertsgaard, North Dakota.
- North Dakota--letters from Charles Mahnken, Fargo, 1890-1891 (Box 4)
  Letters from Charles Mahnken, attorney, Fargo North Dakota.
- North Dakota--letters from L.A. Shattuck, New York, circa 1890-1897 (Box 4)
  Letters from L.A. Shattuck, New York, concerning land in North Dakota.
- North Dakota--Richard Piper, 1890- (Box 4)
  Letters from Richard Piper, North Dakota.
- North Dakota--letters from Joseph Savidge, Philadelphia, 1892-1893 (Box 4)
  Letters from Joseph Savidge, attorney in Philadelphia, concerning legal matters in North Dakota.
- North Dakota--letters from C. Piatt, circa 1891-1894 (Box 4)
  Letters from C. Piatt, North Dakota.
- North Dakota--letters from C. Reeve, Minneapolis, 1889- (Box 4)
  Letters from C. Reeve, Minneapolis, concerning land in North Dakota.
- North Dakota--letters from Miller and Styles, Fargo, 1896- (Box 4)
  Letters from Miller and Styles, attorneys, Fargo North Dakota.
- North Dakota--letters from W.W. Smith, Valley City, 1898- (Box 4)
  Letters from W.W. Smith, real estate and loans, Valley City North Dakota.
- North Dakota--letters from Hiram Truesdale, Minneapolis, 1891- (Box 4)
  Letters from Hiram Truesdale, attorney in Minneapolis, concerning lands in North Dakota.
- North Dakota--letters from C.P. Balkan, Griggs County, 1891- (Box 4)
  Letters from C.P. Balkan, Griggs County North Dakota.
- North Dakota--letters from Harrison Allen, Fargo, 1890- (Box 4)
  Letters from Harrison Allen, Fargo North Dakota.
- North Dakota--letters from James Armstrong, New York, 1889-1890 (Box 4)
  Letters from James Armstrong, legal counsellor in New York, concerning land in North Dakota.
- North Dakota--letters from Curtis & Burdett, Washington D.C., 1889- (Box 4)
  Contains letters from Curtis and Burdett, attorneys and counsellors at law in Washington D.C., concerning legal matters in North Dakota.
- North Dakota--letters from the Dwight Farm and Land Co., 1896- (Box 4)
  Letters from the Dwight Land Co. in North Dakota concerning land in North Dakota.
- North Dakota--letters from D.A. Lindsey, Fargo, 1891- (Box 4)
  Contains letters from D.A. Lindsey law office in Fargo North Dakota.
- North Dakota--letters from the Northwestern Trust Co., Fargo, 1890- (Box 4)
  Contains letters from The Northwestern Trust Co., Fargo North Dakota.
- North Dakota--letters from J.E. Robinson, Fargo, 1897-1898 (Box 4)
  Contains letters from J.E. Robinson, attorney in Fargo North Dakota.
- North Dakota--letters from L.E. Schoonmaker, New York, 1894- (Box 4)
  Contains letters from L.E. Schoonmaker, New York, concerning land in North Dakota.
- North Dakota--letters from Thomas Sporeland, Griggs County, 1891- (Box 4)
  Contains letters from Thomas Sporeland, Griggs County North Dakota.
- Dakota Territory and North Dakota--letters, agreements, and lawsuits, circa 1874-1913; 2 folders (Box 5)
  Contains letters, agreements, and lawsuits concerning business in North Dakota and Dakota Territory.
- North Dakota--horse breeding certificate and correspondence, Cooperstown, 1907- (Box 5)
  Contains correspondence and certificate regarding horse breeding in Cooperstown, North Dakota.
- Dakota Territory--stock receipts for Valley City and Turtle Mountain Railroad, 1881-1882 (Box 5)
  Contains various stock receipts for Valley City and Turtle Mountain Railroad in Dakota Territory.
- Dakota Territory--stock receipts from Dakota Land Co., 1882- (Box 5)
  Contains stock receipts for the Dakota Land Company.
- North Dakota--stock receipt for Burlington, Cedar Rapids, and Northern Railroad, Fargo, 1893- (Box 5)
  Contains a stock receipt for the Burlington, Cedar Rapids and Northern Railroad.
- Dakota Territory--newspaper clipping, 1883- (Box 5)
  Contains a newspaper clipping from Dakota Territory detailing financial information.
- Dakota Territory and North Dakota--loan receipts, scrip receipts, land receipts and tax receipts [folders 1-4 of 6], circa 1882-1913; 4 folders (Box 5)
- Dakota Territory and North Dakota--loan receipts, scrip receipts, land receipts and tax receipts [folders 5-6 of 6], circa 1882-1913; 2 folders (Box 6)
- Dakota Territory--newspaper clipping, circa 1876-1880 (Box 6)
  Contains a newspaper clipping concerning the sale of Red Lake and Pembina Chippewa lands in Dakota Territory.
- Dakota Territory--land scrip receipts from Red Lake and Pembina Chippewa, 1876-1877, 1880 (Box 6)
  Contains land script receipts concerning Red Lake and Pembina Chippewa lands in Dakota Territory.
- Dakota Territory--Sioux land patent, 1884- (Box 6)
  Contains a land patent concerning Sioux lands in Dakota Territory.
- Dakota Territory--land patents for Red Lake and Pembina Chippewa, 1876-1883; 2 folders (Box 6)
- Dakota Territory and North Dakota--deeds and mortgages [folders 1-4 of 19], circa 1874-1878; 4 folders (Box 6)
  Contains deeds, mortgages, abstracts and other papers concerning lands in Dakota Territory and North Dakota.
- Dakota Territory and North Dakota--deeds and mortgages [folders 5-11 of 19], circa 1879-1884; 7 folders (Box 7)
- Dakota Territory and North Dakota--deeds and mortgages [folders 12-19 of 19], circa 1885-1902; 8 folders (Box 8)
- Dakota Territory and North Dakota--title abstracts, circa 1885-1907 (Box 8)
- Minnesota--drug store envelope, Brainerd, undated (Box 8)
  Contains an undated drugstore envelope from the "Post Office Drug Store" in Brainerd Minnesota.
- Minnesota--letters from Albert Wisner, Chicago, 1878-1881 (Box 8)
  Contains letters from Albert Wisner, real estate dealer in Chicago.
- Minnesota--election results from "Scandinavian towns", 1883- (Box 8)
  Contains newspaper clippings of 1883 election results from the "Scandinavian Towns" in Minnesota.
- Minnesota--checks from local banks, 1876-1884 (Box 8)
- Minnesota--Villard hotel sale documents, Brainerd, circa 1886 (Box 8)
  Contains various documents concerning the sale of the Villard Hotel in Brainerd Minnesota.
- Minnesota--Brainerd Contracting Co., circa 1885-1887 (Box 8)
  Contains documents concerning the Brainerd Contracting Co.
- Minnesota--Norwegian/English letter from Mons L. Stene, 1893- (Box 8)
  Contains a letter from Mons L. Stene of Fossum Minnesota, written in Norwegian and English.
- Minnesota--letters from Northern Pacific Railroad, 1880-1896 (Box 8)
  Contains letters from the Northern Pacific Railroad Co.
- Minnesota--tax receipts, circa 1873-1899; 2 folders (Box 9)
  Contains tax receipts from Minnesota; also includes one letter dated 1884.
- Minnesota--letters and documents, circa 1878-1906; 5 folders (Box 9)
  Contains letters along with financial, legal, and other documents concerning business in Minnesota.
- Minnesota--letters and documents, circa 1880-1911; 2 folders (Box 10)
- Minnesota--letters from Charles F. Kindred, 1906-1907 (Box 10)
  Contains letters wriiten by Charles F. Kindred
- Minnesota--land ownership lists, undated (Box 10)
  Contains lists of land ownership, organized by land section.
- Minnesota--deeds and mortgages [folders 1-9 of 17], circa 1874-1882; 9 folders (Box 10)
  Contains various deeds, morgages, and other papers from Minnesota dealings.
- Minnesota--deeds and mortgages [folders 10-17 of 17], circa 1883-1907; 8 folders (Box 11)
- Minnesota--bill from Jennie Jackson, Brainerd, 1886- (Box 11)
  Contains a bill from Jennie Jackson for cutting wood.
- Minnesota--letters and documents from utility and other companies, circa 1883-1886; 5 folders (Box 11)
  Contains letters and documents pertaining to Minnesota utility investments and other companies.
- Minnesota--political survey ledger, circa 1870s-1880s (Box 12)
  Contains a handwritten political survey ledger concerning Mille Lacs county, includes reference to Morrison county. Survey includes nationality, party preference, influential friends, and whether voters were "solid" or "doubtful."
- Minnesota--letters and documents from utility and other companies, circa 1887-1914; 9 folders (Box 13)
- Minnesota--letters related to Weyerhauser, Chippewa Lumber and Boom Co., circa 1890 (Box 13)
  Contains letters concerning Weyerhauser company, Chippewa Lumber and Boom Company, and "lumbermen." Includes maps.
- Minnesota--letter to Mayor of Brainerd related to a gas plant ordinance, 1914- (Box 13)
  Contains a letter to the mayor of Brainerd, Minnesota, and an ordinance pertaining to a gas plant.
- Minnesota--letters and documents related to Brainerd utilities, circa 1880s-1890s; 3 folders (Box 14)
  Contains miscellaneous letters and documents pertaining to utilities in Brainerd, Minnesota; includes undated documents.
- Northern Pacific Railroad land examination ledgers, circa 1880s (Box 14)
  Contains two Northern Pacific Railroad land examination ledgers, each containing approx. 100 diagrams of lands.
- Land maps of Dakota Territory, North Dakota, and Minnesota, circa 1890s (Box 14)
- Land maps of Minnesota, circa 1888 (Box 14)
  Contains three land maps from Minnesota on Northern Pacific Railroad stationary.
- Land maps of Minnesota, circa 1890s (Box 14)
  Contains land maps, unclear if Minnesota or North Dakota.
- Land maps of Minnesota, undated (Box 14)
  Contains land maps, possibly of Sandstone, Minnesota.
- Land maps of Minnesota, undated (Box 14)
  Contains land maps, possibly from Otter Tail county, Minnesota.
- Land maps of Minnesota, undated; 2 folders (Box 14)
  Contains land maps, some drawn on Minnesota stationary.
- Land maps of Ontario Canada, unidentified land maps, and documents related to W.A. Kindred, circa 1870-1903 (Box 15)
  Contains land maps and documents--from Ontario, Canada--concerning W.A. Kindred and business proceedings including mining.
- Illinois--tax receipts from Cook county, Illinois, circa 1876-1881 (Box 15)
- Pennsylvania--land map of Grenoble, 1894 (Box 15)
- Letters and documents, circa 1878-1903 (Box 15)
  Contains letters and documents from various states and sources, including deeds, mortgages, and other ephemera.